Everybody, once again,
welcome back to more
about our data frames
and pandas in Python.
In this content video,
we're going to talk about
descriptive statistics,
some sorting, and then a
really easy way that you
can transpose a data frame.
Descriptive statistics,
one of the reasons
pandas is so awesome is because
to get statistics on your
data frame, it's literally as
easy as just writing described.
Let's actually jump over to our
code space. we'll go ahead and do
an example. So as always import pandas
and let's open up our data frame.
You really should like type
this all out so that it's not
the same in every single video
but know that you can fast
forward at least ten seconds of
this video and not miss think.
Okay,
and there's our data frame,
perfect. So what we're going to
do is we are going to run the
dataframe.describe function.
Okay, so what this gives us is
statistical overview of our data frame.
As you can see, we've got the
count, the mean, the standard
deviation, the min, the max, and a
couple of percentiles about our data.
So for example, we've got in our
count column, we've got our passenger
ID, we've got 891 records of that,
whereas in age, we've got 714.
And that gives us a couple more
of our different columns. Note
that it doesn't give us the
categorical columns, it's more just
giving us the numerical columns,
right? So I'm not getting one
like cabin number, for example,
because the cabin numbers are
strings. And so it can't really
give me the standard deviation of
string values. So we've got the
mean, the standard deviation,
again, the minimum, the maximum,
and yeah, just percentiles about it.
So that's super, super helpful if
we're wanting to get some quick,
just a quick look at our data
here. So another thing that
we can do, let's print out
the average age, for example.
That'll be data frame at the column age.
Here's the mean age, 29, super nice.
Here's the total survive. Let's
find the total survivors. That'll
be our DataFrame survived.
We'll do a sum.
So again, these are more
things that we've used with
our regular Python file, but
now we're able to use them
on columns of our DataFrame
too, which is so helpful.
Let's do one more. let's
find out our unique ports.
Do a .unique.
So there we go, we've got the
s, the c, and the q, and then
I think a couple of them are
are blank, so not a number.
So I'm not expecting you guys to
like remember all of these different
methods and functions, but just
kind of being aware of like all
the things that we can do with the
data in our data frames is so so
helpful okay let's talk for a
minute about sorting data frames so
there's some basic and easy
ways to do this let's say we've
got a data frame let's call
it expensive passengers we
did this in our last content
video I believe we'll set that
we'll sign out the value of
data frame dot sorts values.
So that's a nice function there.
Sort values takes a couple of arguments.
So you can say, or you can see
here, it says by string, sequence
string. So what this is
saying is it's asking for some
arguments from us. So I'm going
to say, let's sort it by our fair.
By equals fair. So we're
assigning a default in a way.
So by is fair. And then
let's say ascending
equals false. So it'll
be descending order.
And then let's output
our expensive passengers.
There we go.
Oops.
What did I do wrong?
Did type bool and I gave it a string. Oh,
I did give it a string. What about that?
I gave it false in quotation
marks, not false. There
we go. Okay, so here's our
most expensive passenger. It's
Mr. Thomas Drake Martinez
is Cardenza, and he paid
512 money units to ride the
Titanic. I wonder if he had
one parent or child with him. He had
one parent child with him, so I'm
not sure what he paid so much for.
Maybe he had a really good cabin.
I guess he was in first class, but
hey, so were some of our zero paid
people, so that's curious. I
wonder why that is. A data quality
question that we can start asking
now that we can see our our data
laid out and we you know we could
also do something like let's filter
this down to name maybe it's too
much data for us we want to see the
name and the fair and their class
that we've got a little bit less
going on we could do that too
there it is so that simplifies what
we're looking at okay let's do a
sort by multiple columns so let's say
we wanted to sort by our class
and then our name maybe that's a
pretty not that pretty normal thing
to do so sorted titanic we'll assign
that to the value of our data
frame dot sort values this time
what we'll do is we'll say by whoops
by is equal to and we'll give it
a data frame we'll say P class and
then let's do name and then we'll
say ascending equals first true and
then false so ascending and then
descending so we want to see first
second third and then we want
to see an alphabetical order going
down and then let's output that
but let's only output the name
column the p class and their age full
ascending right
I did oh I left off a
bracket that'll do it
uh-oh extra bracket there we go
okay so we've got our class oops
they're actually in well maybe we
want this to be true as well they're
actually in opposite alphabet of
quarter there we go okay so here is
the passenger with their class
so in a very first we've got miss
elizabeth walton allen who is in first
class and going on and on and on.
Okay, and then last thing for
this content video is transposing,
which is also pretty easy to do.
So let's say we've got our data frame.
Let's do a head, and let's
take just the first row,
and we want to transpose
that. We'll just throw
a capital T on the end
there. It's an attribute.
And now you can see that
we've got our very first row,
and all of those items that
were columns are now in rows.
So that's going to be everything for this
content video. Thank you for watching.